Preliminary Guide to the Hermann Borchardt Papers, 1918-1960s RL.00128
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hermann Borchardt papers
1918-1960s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Borchardt, Hermann, 1888-
RL.00128
4.2 Linear Feet
German writer and intellect who escaped a Nazi concentration camp and immigrated to New York in 1937. Collection consists of correspondence between Borchardt and several friends, including several news clippings and photographs. Subjects discussed include the emergence of Nazi Germany under Hitler and the origins and consequences of World War II. The remainder of the collection consists of literary manuscripts, drafts, and notes from Borchardt's writings, as well as some correspondence and newspaper clippings. Many of the materials are not in order and are in poor condition. Writings are in German and English.
3200 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hermann Borchardt Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007.
Biographical Note
Hermann Borchardt was a German intellectual with Marxist leanings who left Germany in 1933 following Hitler's rise to power. He moved to Russia to teach German, but his exposure to the oppression he found there led him to reverse his political leanings and become an outspoken critic of communism. His family was expelled from Russia in 1936, and returned to Germany. Borchardt spent 10 months in Nazi concentration camps before finally being allowed to leave Germany and immigrate to the United States, where his family later joined him. He continued to write books, short stories, and articles criticising communism. His best work is considered to be The Conspiracy of the Carpenters, published in 1943; other works include Philosophische Grundbegriffe (1927); The Bloody Deeds of Germersheim Before the Eternal Judge, Music of the Near Future, The Red Document (1929); The Brethren of Halberstadt (1938); and The Wife of the Police-Commissionaire (1946). He died of a heart attack in 1951.
Borchardt's youngest son, Frank, was born in New York City, and eventually became a professor of German Languages at Duke University.
Collection Overview
The original collection consists of correspondence between Borchardt and several friends, including several news clippings and photographs. Subjects discussed include the emergence of Nazi Germany under Hitler and the origins and consequences of World War II. They despise Hitler's tactics, expressed dismay with British Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain's policy of appeasement, and criticized Hitler's deal with Russia's Stalin (i.e. the German-Russian Non-Aggression Pact of 1939). The collection also makes reference to German playwright Bertolt Brecht, whose views of war the correspondents agreed with.
The accession (2008-0158) appears to consist largely of literary manuscripts, drafts, and notes from Borchardt's writings, as well as some correspondence and newspaper clippings. Many of the materials are not in order and are in poor condition. Writings are in German and English. This addition is unprocessed.
Drafts (documents); Translations (documents); Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- Germany; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Borchardt, Hermann, 1888-; Hitler, Adolf; Germany -- Treaties, etc. -- Soviet Union, 1939 Aug. 23; Borchardt, Hermann, 1888-; Chamberlain, Neville, 1869-1940; Brecht, Bertolt -- 1898-1956
- Letters, 1934-1950, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  This portion of the collection (55 items) includes correspondence between Borchardt and several friends, including several news clippings and photographs. Subjects discussed include the emergence of Nazi Germany under Hitler and the origins and consequences of World War II. They despise Hitler's tactics, expressed dismay with British Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain's policy of appeasement, and criticized Hitler's deal with Russia's Stalin (i.e. the German-Russian Non-Aggression Pact of 1939). The collection also makes reference to German playwright Bertolt Brecht, whose views of war the correspondents agreed with.
  - Letters, 1934-1950 (Box 1)
- Accession (2008-0158), 1918-1960s, 7 boxes
  Accession (2008-0158) (3150 items; 4.2 lin. ft.; dated 1910s-1960s and no date) consists of literary manuscripts, drafts, and notes from Borchardt's writings, as well as some correspondence and newspaper clippings. Many of the materials are not in order and are in poor condition. Writings are in German and English.
  Arrangement note
  This addition is unprocessed. Materials have been refoldered and German titles have been transcribed from the original folders to the best of our ability. Many pages were loose and unlabelled.
  - The Brethren of Halberstadt, Acts I-II (Box 1A)
  - The Smoke Rose Up Forever (Box 1A)
  - Conspiracy of the Carpenters (Box 1A)
  - Louise, Act I (Box 1A)
  - Text, no label, pages 340-770 (Box 1A)
  - Printed materials
    - Griechische Bildwerke und Der Stille Garten (Box 1B)
    - Captivity, by Fred Uhlman (Box 1B)
  - Calendar, no year (Box 1B)
  - Moritz von Schwind (Box 1B)
  - The Brethren of Halberstadt, Act III (Box 2)
  - Weinhold manuscripts (Box 2)
  - Geschichte eines bosen Gewissens (Box 2)
  - Loose pages, no label (Box 2)
  - Froanziger Jahre (Box 2)
  - Short story (Box 2)
  - Text, no label (Box 2)
  - Michael Schirmer, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Antonia Wellhöhner, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Tale of a Noblewoman (Box 2)
  - Dritter Akt. (Box 3)
  - Rudolf K. Kommer: Hotel Ambassador (The Smoke Rose Up Forever, Acts I-IV) (Box 3)
  - 1914 and 1918 (Box 3)
    Articles, clippings, correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings and miscellaneous materials (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, to Mimi [Hermann's wife, Dorothy Redmer Borchardt] from Baby, 1960s (Box 3)
  - Die Verschwörungder der Zimmerleüte (Box 4)
  - Text, no label, p. 5-138 (Box 4)
  - Loose pages (Box 4)
  - Braunes (?) (Box 4)
  - Die Verschwörung der Zimmerleüte (Box 4)
  - Luise: Dritter Akt. Das Gericht (Box 4)
  - Loose drafts (in German) (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Nächte (Box 4)
  - Methodik-Minsk, 1935 (Box 4)
  - I Akt: Die Razzia (Box 4)
  - Der Verlorene Haufe (The Vanguard), 1939 (Box 5)
  - The Conspiracy of the Carpenters (Box 5)
  - Tale of a Noblewoman I (Box 5)
  - Geschichte Einer Edelfrau (Box 5)
  - Club der Hamloser Angefaugener Roman (?) (Box 5)
  - Die Nacht der Versöhnung (Box 5)
  - Loose pages, no label (Box 5)
  - Loose pages, no label (Box 6)
  - 1923 (Box 6)
  - A Thaler und A Pfenning und No Reich to the Germans (Box 6)
  - Loose pages, no label (Box 6)
  - Das Paradies des Kleinen Otto (Box 6)
  - Tale of a Noblewoman II (Box 6)
  - Der Kleine Engel in Österreich (Box 6)
  - The Smoke Rose Up Forever (Box 6)
  - Loose pages, no label (Box 6)
  - Austria newspaper, 1948 (Box 6)
  - Clippings on foreign alliances, domestic peace, and the Far East (Box 7)
  - Loose pages, no label (Box 7)
  - Drafts of chapters
    - Die Sünde des Erafen Gotter (II) (Box 7)
    - Mann und Frau (III) (Box 7)
    - Erste Begegnung (VII) (Box 7)
    - Diner bei Gotter (VIII) (Box 7)
  - Sofort zü Arbe Schreiben (Box 7)
  - Roman: Das jahr 1918 (Box 7)
  - 1918: Schwester Martha (Box 7)
  - Die Brüder von Halberstadt (Box 7)
  - Schluss Rapibel (Box 7)
  - Kapital (?) (Box 7)
  - Loose pages and manuscripts (Box 7)
  - Short stories
    - Eros Stark Wie der Tod (Box 7)
    - The Legend of the Gothamists (Box 7)
    - Tag der Befreiung (Box 7)
    - Der Schwarze Freitag (Box 7)
    - Verpöbelung der Gebildeten durch exakte Wissenschaft (Box 7)
    - Erstes Kapitel (Box 7)
  - German National Character (Part I) (Box 7)
  - Outside Education (Part II) (Box 7)
  - Make Them Forget (Part III) (Box 7)
  - Secondary Schools (Part IV) (Box 7)
  - Uprising of a Ruling Class (Part V) (Box 7)